观众朋友们 这是2008年北京奥运会
Hello, everyone, this is the 2008 Beijing Olympics'
中国女排对阵美国女排的比赛现场
Women's volleyball match between China and USA.
卫冕冠军中国女排 是中国最受欢迎的运动球队之一
The holders are one of the favourite teams among the locals
今天拥有主场优势
with a home advantage today.
这场比赛预计有三亿人收看
This match is predicted to have 300 million viewers.
今天的比赛之所以如此引人注目
This match is in the spotlight
还有另外一个原因
for another reason.
对 你没有看错
That's correct.
这是美国队主教练
Team USA's head coach
郎平
Lang Ping.
她是著名的铁鎯头
Nicknamed the Iron Hammer.
曾经和队友们一起创造了 八十年代五连冠的辉煌奇迹
Achieving a legendary feat of 5 world championships in a row with her team.
现在郎平身穿美国队的队服
Lang Ping, in the navy blue uniform
用英文指挥比赛
directs the players from the USA bench in English.
郎平今天的对手是她多年的队友和战友
Ping's opponent today is her friend of many years.
你知道的
You know
中国队和美国队的比赛
when China plays the USA
永远不是一场比赛那么简单
it's never simple.
新来的同志吧
Welcome, new comrade.
你好 我是女排的领队
Hello, I'm the team manager.
来 我给你介绍一下情况
Let me show you around.
这是副教练 在带她们练扣球
This is the assistant coach leading the spiking practice.
这个
Her here
这是5号 我们的主攻手
is No. 5, our outside hitter.
身高一米八零八一队过来的
1.8m tall, from Bayi Volleyball team.
干部家庭出身 但是特别能吃苦
From a civil servant family, works extremely hard.
基本功特别好
Great basic techniques.
在场上能攻能防
Can both attack and defence well.
蓝衣服那个
The girl in blue
也是主攻手
also an outside hitter.
她应该是世界上最矮的主攻手之一
She's probably the shortest hitter in the world.
但你别瞧她个儿不高
She might not be tall
手上有绝活
but she's got her own techniques
什么乱七八糟的球都能给你招呼过去
to spike anything set to her.
8号是我们的替补二传
This is backup setter, No. 8.
12号 9号 2号
No. 12, No. 9 and No. 2
都是我们的副攻
are our middle blockers.
看这位
Here.
主力二传
Our setter.
队长
The captain.
脑子好传球的节奏感和手感都好
Excellent rhythm and touch on sets, but
就是有一点 脾气倔 在场上受不得气
temperamental, and at times unwilling to take orders.
这个是4号
This is No. 4.
一传和拦网都非常好
She sets and blocks extremely well.
一般人像这么蹲个十几下 腿不得发抖
Most people can do around 20 before collapsing
她每天都蹲二百下
but she does 200 squats every day.
这个副攻
That middle blocker
是你们福建老乡
like you, is from Fujian.
扣球和拦网动作都非常漂亮
Her spikes and blocks are beautiful
就是有一点 胆小 说话声也小
but she's jittery and softly spoken.
这是1号老队员
That's No. 1, our last captain
出了名的要球不要命
who's willing to risk her life to save a ball.
浑身都是伤
Injuries all over her body.
膝盖软骨都磨没了
Her knee caps are all worn down.
那边蹲杠铃那位叫郎平
That's Lang Ping, doing squats with weights
北京姑娘
is from Beijing.
十八岁就进国家队了
Called into the national team at 18.
入队的时候
Before coming here
负重不到三十公斤
she couldn't even lift 30 kilos.
教练让她练体能
Coach has ordered
单次深蹲不到一百公斤 就不让她碰球
unless she can lift 100 kilos, she's not to practise with a ball.
这是教练在特意培养她
This is how Coach trains her.
队员们也在帮她
Her teammates are also helping her.
我帮你拿
Let me help you.
起来
Get up!
你们越觉得累就会越累
Sitting there makes you feel more tired.
人是有惰性的
People are naturally lazy.
起来
Get up!
这位就不用介绍了吧
Our coach needs no introduction.
起来了起来了
Come on, up!
刚才你们练滚翻的时候
When you girls were rolling on the floor
在地上多赖了两秒钟
you stayed 2 seconds too long.
记住
Remember!
在球场上两秒钟 就是胜负
2 seconds is long enough for victory on court.
每个人加练十个球
Everyone, 10 more spikes!
你
You!
别哭
Don't cry!
中国女排 流血不流泪
China women's volleyball shed blood but not tears.
我就是不行 我不练了
I can't do it! I quit!
你
You!
想练就练 不想练就不练
You think you can start and stop whenever you like?
不行
No!
你今天不练
If you stop training now
明天一早我就练你
we'll continue with you tomorrow morning.
来啊
Come on!
继续啊
Again!
要想去日本拿世界杯冠军
If this China team is to win the World Cup
就要建立起一支我们自己的
they must be as strong as western teams
全面型球队
and become a well-rounded team.
教练
Coach
女排这方面我从来没有接触过
I've never worked in women's volleyball.
一点也不了解
I don't know anything about it.
我不知道你们
I don't get why you asked me to be...
我们想找个陪打教练
We want a man as their hitting partner.
教练
Coach
组织上没跟我说这个
the party didn't tell me...
这个陪打教练
We need a hitting partner who can
是要了解扮演我们的 主要竞争对手的技术手段
copy the playing techniques of our main competitors.
教练
Coach
上面跟我说是借调期四十五天
the order I have is to stay here for 45 days.
但是没说要当女排的陪打教练
No one mentioned being a hitting partner.
另外
Plus
我怕我的能力达不到要求
I don't think I'm qualified enough.
小同志
Comrade
这是一个很重要的工作
this is a very important position.
欢迎你加入中国女排的训练
Welcome to China women's national volleyball team training.
来 王干事 这边
Come this way, Officer Wang.
辛苦你了 坐了两天两夜火车专程跑过来
You must be very tired after 2 days of train ride.
不辛苦
Don't mention it.
教练
Coach
我给您介绍一下
let me introduce him to you.
这是国家体委科教司的王干事
He's technical officer Wang from Administration of Sport
从北京连夜赶过来的
coming straight from Beijing.
教练您好
Nice to meet you, Coach.
一 二
One, Two.
一二
计算器我没有接触过
What is computer technology exactly?
计算器就是计算机
It's an electronic brain.
相当于一千个人脑
That's equal to a thousand human brains.
可以进行非常复杂的运算
It can perform complex operations.
运动员的技术特点
A player's strengths
习惯线路和战术变化都能够被分析出来
usual way of playing and tactics can all be analysed.
根据我们最新获得的消息
According to the latest report
美国主教练塞林格已经将计算器技术
US head coach Selinger has begun using computer technology
运用到美国女排的训练和比赛当中
to enhance the training and match performance of his team.
也就是说
Which means
我们所有运动员
all our athletes
他们都了如指掌
are being calculated.
当然也包括您
Including you.
我们能弄到一个机器吗
Can we get this computer thing?
中科院倒是有
There is only one at the Academy of Sciences
一个大卡车都装不下
but I've heard it couldn't even fit into a truck.
全国会操作的也没几个人
Very few people know how to use it.
运用到女排上面来可能不太现实
I don't think they'd let us use it for volleyball.
哦 对了
One more thing.
塞林格还说
Selinger has also mentioned
未来体育靠的不是人 是科技
technology will be the future of sports, not humans.
谁掌握科技 谁就能赢
Whoever has the technologies, wins.
谢谢
Thank you.
把网升高十五厘米
Raise the net by 15cm.
练
Carry on!
跳
Jump!
高了跳
Higher!
你扣这种菜球有什么用
You call those spikes?
你现在手软
If you let them off easy now
明天她们比赛就丢分
they'll lose points during the match.
加力
Harder!
别躲往前顶
Don't dodge! Harder!
往前顶
Go towards the ball!
你模仿的力量和角度都不够
That's not enough power and curve!
接球
Catch the ball.
美国人不会对你手软
The Americans will not show you mercy!
日本人不会对你手软
The Japanese will not show you mercy!
来
Come on!
我们这么干
Do you think my method of training
计算器能计算出来吗
can be calculated by a computer?
继续
Keep going.
来 顶
Come on!
大家都练完走了
Everyone's gone.
钢铁不是一天可以炼成的
Rome was not built in a day.
哎 算了
Screw it.
走了
I'm leaving.
反正你也举不起一百公斤
You can't lift 100 kilos anyway.
明天我就跟教练说你举到了
I'll tell the Coach tomorrow that you've done it.
我先去吃饭了
I'm going for dinner.
你干吗
Hey, what are you doing?
好了 我看见了 你快放下来
Okay! I've seen it. Put it down!
你腰不要了
You wanna kill yourself!?
我十八岁就进了国家队
I was called up to the national team at 18.
别人都以为我一直顺
Everyone tells me I'm lucky
却不知道我平时练得有多苦
without knowing how hard I've worked.
没想到
I didn't know
进了国家队我连球都摸不到
I couldn't even touch a ball here.
老队员技术都比我强
The experienced players are technically better.
除了能比别人吃苦我还能干吗
All I can do is work harder.
可在这儿
But the thing is
每个人都能吃苦 我连这个也赢不了别人
everyone here works hard, so I can't even win with that.
我现在没别的路可走了
There are no other choices for me.
不能考大学了
I can't go to university.
只能硬着头皮练下去
I can only keep my head down and practise.
一万年太久
10 thousand years are too long
只争朝夕
seize the day, seize the hour.
打得赢就打 打不赢就走
Fight if you can win, run if you will lose.
有人活在梦里
Some people live in a dream world.
有人喜欢现实
Some people live in reality.
有人喜欢把一种变成另一种
And some make one into the other.
在说什么 我听不懂
What is that? I don't get that.
你知道吗
Do you know
从国旗最下边到地面的距离是三米三二
from the bottom of the flag to the floor is 3.32m.
那是海曼 （美国队主攻） 的摸高
That's the spiking height of Flo Hyman (USA's outside hitter).
总有一天我会超过她的
I will jump higher one day.
你一个替补
You're just a backup
先打上主力再说吧
talk when you're a starter.
我深蹲已经超过一百公斤了
I've already lifted 100 kilos.
我明天就可以碰球了
I'll be practising with a ball tomorrow.
快点快点 郎平
Hurry up, Lang Ping.
你快一点
Count faster!
这是国家队
This is the national team.
不是跑江湖
We're not on the streets.
吹口哨像什么样
Don't whistle like that.
教练 你为什么还是 单把我一个人撇出来
Coach, why am I still not training with the team?
陪她扣一万次球
Spike 10 thousand balls with her.
好
OK.
你答应过我
You promised
蹲够一百公斤我就可以参加分组训练了
when I lift 100 kilos, I can join the team.
你是蹲够了一百公斤 可是她们比你蹲得还多
You have lifted 100 kilos, but they have lifted more.
你扣一万次球的时候 她们已经扣了五万次了
You spike 10 thousand, they spike 50 thousand.
帮我接球
Catch the ball for me.
上手飘球
Overhead floater.
弧度再高一些
It needs to go higher.
再接一个
Another one.
挥臂动作放松 腰背挺直
Relax your arm, straighten your back
击准球
and hit in the middle.
当你的判断成为下意识的时候
Only when your judgement becomes your instincts
你在赛场上
during a match
才可能出现在正确的位置
can you be in the right position.
下意识怎么来
How does it become instinct?
训练来的
By training.
不是一般的训练
Not just any training.
而是千百万次上亿次
It needs to be done millions, even billions of times.
不断重复的训练
Endless repetition.
只有坚持下来的人才能走到最后
Only those who persevere will succeed.
这场比赛
This match...
你到替补
you're on the bench.
郎平打主力
Ping will start.
教练 您放心吧
Don't worry, Coach.
我会配合好 让郎平达到锻炼目的
I'll help Ping reach her potential.
你
You!
你今天去江苏男排打接应
You play opposite for the Jiangsu men's team.
你说搞这种形式主义有什么用
What's the point of this?
难道要我们跟她们真打吗
Are we supposed to take this seriously?
向江苏男排学习
Learn from Jiangsu men's team.
向你学习
Thank you for the opportunity.
加油 加油
Come on! come on!
一 二 加油
One, two, come on!
好球
Well played!
给我真打
Let's kick their ass!
看我手
Look at my hand...
看一下我手 接好一传
Look at my hand. Focus on the receive.
有机会打跑动
Let's have more movement.
一 二 加油
One, two, come on!
看一下我手势
Look at my hand.
重心降低
Stay low.
防守 防守
Defence!
没关系 下一个再来
It's alright. Focus on the next point.
球再给高一点
Set the ball higher.
别着急 急了也不要让对手看出来
Don't rush. Don't let your opponent know you're rushing.
给我
Give me!
Let me!
给我
I've got it.
好球
Good job!
平时我练你们确实苦
Do you now get
现在你们应该明白了吧
why I've been training you girls so hard?
只有这么练
It's all those training sessions
中国最优秀的男排才会跟你们真打
that's pushing the men to play seriously.
这个机会很难得 把握住这个机会
Seize this opportunity.
小伙子
Kiddo.
平时她们拿命来练
The women here put their lives on the line everyday
就是为了在赛场上能够打出来
to show what they can do during matches.
如果你心里这点事还过不去的话
Get your head straight.
你对得起她们吗
They need you.
你确实是个陪打教练
You are a hitting partner.
但是你已经是中国女排 不可缺少的一员了
But you are an important member of this team.
中国女排是什么
What is the women's national volleyball team?
中国女排没有你
It's not about you.
没有我
Not about me.
只有我们
It's all of us.
加油
Come on.
自己去抓每一个机会
Take every opportunity we get.
加油
Come on.
加把劲
Fight for this.
中国女排 加油
China women's national team, go!
你要知道
Let me tell you
人最不愿意的就是 年轻的时候对不起自己
young people just want to do right by themselves.
年纪大了才会发现
Eventually they'll find
对不起的都是别人
they've only wronged other people.
郎平
Lang Ping!
你今天要是打得赢我
If you can beat us
我这辈子都陪着你练
I'll train with you for life.
向中国女排学习
Learn from the women's national volleyball team.
你们马上就要打日本世界杯了
You'll play at the World Cup in Japan soon.
为了电视录像 两边都会有这样的强光
They'll have strong lights for TV on both sides.
你们要提前适应
You must get used to them.
你看球场上
Look at the court.
3号一米九零
No. 3 is 1.9m tall.
和苏联的波尔科娃一样
He's the same height as Soviet's Pavlova.
7号一米九六
No. 7 is 1.96m tall.
是美国队海曼的身高
Same height as US' Flo Hyman.
10号的净跳高度和古巴的佩雷斯一样
No. 10 spiking height is the same as Cuba's Pérez.
我们陪打教练的力量身型
Our training partner's power and build
和江上由美相似
are similar to Yumi Egami's.
郎平一米八四
Lang Ping is 1.84m.
是我们最接近欧美的主攻
She's our best match to a western outside hitter.
其实今天就是一场模拟战
This is a test match.
如果我们可以跟男排抗衡
If we can match a men's team today
明天
tomorrow
我们就能拿世界冠军
we can win the World Cup.
今天大家在场上配合得不好
You ladies ignored teamwork today.
继续加练
We keep training.
从队长开始
We'll start with the captain.
防三十个好球
Make 30 good saves.
加油
Come on!
现在已经大年初一了
It's already New Year!
让她们过年吧
Let them take a break.
负十二个
Negative 12.
有谁替她
Who wants to take her place?
我来
Me!
加油
Come on!
三十个
That's 30.
吃饭
Let's eat.
闺女
Baby.
妈
Mom.
是你们教练接我来的
The coach sent me here.
别哭
Don't cry.
我承认我有私心
I do have selfish intentions.
66年
In 1966
中国男排
the men's national team
拿了世界第九
came in 9th.
大家信心倍增 觉得中国排球
Everyone was confident
一定能够搞上去
we can reach the top.
没有想到
Who would have thought
之后的十年没球打
we'd stop playing for the next 10 years.
我这心里边就憋着一口气
There's been a dagger in my heart ever since.
我第一次出国
The first time I went abroad.
走进宾馆房间里边 我傻了
I was in awe of the hotel room.
冰箱
Refrigerator
彩电
colour TV
空调
air conditioner
我没见过
I've never seen them before.
那一宿我真的没睡觉
I couldn't sleep that night.
我望着窗外的高楼大厦
Looking at the buildings outside
我哭了
I cried.
中国太落后了
China is so far behind
我们怎么办
what can we do?
是坐在这里唉声叹气
Do we just sit here and sigh
还是把失去的损失抢回来
or fight and catch up with the lost time?
现在我们国家搞改革开放
The country is reforming to open up
中国体育走在最前面
sports in China is a priority.
我们比不上人家的训练条件
We don't have the facilities other countries have
只有靠比别人拚命才能赢
so we have to work harder to have any chance of winning.
我们国家太需要这个奖牌了
The Chinese people need to be world champions.
我们要证明给他们所有人看
We need to prove to everyone
中国人
us Chinese
行的
are great.
来
Come on.
只要能让你们拿冠军
I'll do whatever it takes
你们让我做什么都可以
to make you women the world champions.
中国女排
China women's national volleyball team
一 二 加油
One, two, come on!
起高点
Higher.
注意动作
Watch your movements!
跟日本队打光是强攻也不行
We can't beat them by heavy attacks.
要结合轻拐 轻吊
We need a combination of soft touches.
你们一定要注意江上由美的网口变化
Watch out for Egami's quick change of pace.
没有人能笑着拿世界冠军
No one can win the World Cup with a smile on their face.
继续
Go on.
加油
Come on!
你带头说一说日本队的特点
You start with what's special about the Japanese team.
你还记得那句英语吗
Do you still remember that English sentence?
我爱我的祖国
I love my motherland.
我爱祖国的清晨
I love the morning of my motherland.
日本队个子不高
The Japanese are quite short.
防守好
Defence well.
特别不容易被打死
Hard to be defeated.
所以我们跟她们打
When we face them next time
要慢跳 快伸手
we need to time our jumps with quick hands.
手要硬
Strong arms.
避免破坏性拦网
To make good blocks.
一定要准备多打来回球
And prepare ourselves for long rallies.
跟她们比拚劲 比韧劲
Have to fight till the bitter end.
我们要利用她们的套路打她们
We can fight back by playing their style.
同时也不能让她们摸清我们的套路
but have to cover our tracks.
继续看
Let's continue.
拼啊
Go!
再不拼就没机会了
This is our last chance!
1981年
That's all
日本世界杯出赛人员名单已读完毕
for the 1981 squad to Japan.
陪打教练
Hitting partner
这次不随队出征
will not be travelling with us.
先天条件这个东西
Sometimes when it comes to DNA
有的时候确实是比不了
we really can't fight with nature.
你摸到三米三二了吗
Have you reached 3.32m yet?
但排球
But volleyball
不是一个人的事情
is not about personal heroics.
你应该多看看你的队友
Look to your teammates.
你现在最应该做的
What you should do
就是接受现实
is accept reality.
接受现实
Accept reality?
所以你甘心一辈子当陪打教练
So you're willing to be a hitting partner for life?
当陪打教练怎么了
And what's wrong with that?
可以陪着你们拿世界冠军
I'll be next to you when you win world championships.
我们不可能打一辈子球
We can't play for life.
以后打不动了怎么办
What happen when we can't move anymore?
你就没想过
You've not thought about
当中国女排的主教练吗
being the head coach?
你好几天都没睡好觉了
You haven't slept in a while.
一会儿上了飞机要好好休息
Try to get some sleep on the plane.
姐姐们好
Hello.
你好
Nice to meet you.
两杯咖啡
2 coffee, please.
为你保驾护航祝你成功
Hope you all come back as champions!
谢谢
Thanks.
我提议我们合张影吧
I think we should take a group photo.
太苦了
It's so bitter.
有一股中药味
Tastes like Chinese medicine.
郎平
Ping...
有人织的前身
One of us did the front
有人织的后身
another did the back
有人织袖子
someone did the sleeves
还有人挑针织衣领
then there's the collar.
大家七手八脚
It's a group effort.
每个人多少都织了几针
Everyone at least did a few stitches.
就是缝合得不太平整
Even though it's not very neat
袖口也不一样大
and the sleeves are different size.
我想
I want to...
等你有一天当上了教练
One day when you're the head coach
以后有的是机会出去
you'll get your chance to travel.
郎平 走了 登机了
Ping! Time to board.
走了
Let's go.
观众朋友们
Hello everyone.
我们在日本大阪体育馆向大家转播
We're at the Osaka Gymnasium
第三届世界杯女子排球比赛
live at the 3rd FIVB Women's Volleyball World Cup.
中国女排同日本女排
The match between China and Japan
争夺冠亚军比赛的实况
for the championship.
这段时间的比赛里
During the match so far
中国队打得有些急躁 频频失误
the Chinese team has been looking tense, rushing their plays.
加油
Come on!
日本队发球
Japan serves.
这是第四局的比赛
This is the 4th set.
场上的气氛异常地紧张
The atmosphere is highly intense.
日本队防守非常好
Japan's defense is nearly perfect.
她们极力地扑救每一个球
They are doing all they can to save a ball.
中国队扣球
China spikes.
出界
It goes out.
现在的比数是4比8
It's 8 to 4.
日本队领先
Japan is in the lead.
日本队不愧是东洋魔女
The nickname "Toyo Witch" sure suits the Japanese.
她们的防守实在是太好了
Their defense is impossible to penetrate.
日本队老是打不死
The Japanese do play for their lives.
还越打越顺
They are on a high.
中国队打得很被动
Team China's offense looks shut down.
陷入了僵局
It's a stalemate.
3号扣球不过网
No. 3's spike hits the net.
中国队又失一分
China loses another point.
她太着急了
Her attack was rushed.
你瞧你们这破球
What a terrible spike.
4比9
9 to 4.
日本队领先
Japan leads.
日本队发球得分
Japan aces on serve.
这段时间里
For the last few points
中国队主要是一传打得不好
China's main problem has been erroneous first passes.
中国队怎么样了
What's going on now?
中国队输了
China's losing.
输了
Again.
中国队双人拦网
A two-man block from China.
球打手出界
The ball goes out.
中国队再次出现失误
China makes another mistake.
现在日本队发球
Japan serves.
得分
Another point.
日本队在比赛里取得了主动
Japan is controlling the play now
中国姑娘们在比赛之前 就做好了最艰苦的准备
but China has prepared for the worst.
还没结束
It's not over yet.
拿回来
Let's turn it around!
好
Yes!
一 二 加油
One, two, come on!
日本队再扣
Japan spikes again.
中国队7号跌坐在地上
China's No. 7 falls on her hips.
她艰难地爬了起来
She supports herself up.
日本队再次组织进攻
Japan gets ready for another attack.
日本队再扣
Japan spikes again.
球垫飞了
The ball flies out.
日本队赢得了第四局比赛的胜利
Japan wins the 4th set.
接应的位置没有人了
China has no other opposite hitter.
中国队的教练要如何应对呢
How will their Coach handle this?
教练
Coach!
这是我最后一场比赛了
This is my last match.
让我再拼一次吧
Please let me have a go at it!
准备
Get ready.
好
Yes!
前四局已经过去了
Those 4 sets are in the past
什么都不用想
don't think about them.
我现在只要求你们想一件事
I need you to think about one thing only.
我们是在什么地方打球
Think about where you're playing now.
我们是中国人
We are Chinese.
你们代表中华民族
And you're representing the people of China.
这场球如果拿不下来的话
If you don't win this match
你们后悔一辈子
all of you will regret this for life.
加油
Come on.
别急 拼了
Let's fight.
加油
Come on!
一 二 加油
One, two, come on!
她还能打比赛吗
Can she still play?
竟然被逼到这一步也很厉害呢
I didn't know they're this desperate.
观众的掌声非常非常大
The crowd's applause is thunderous.
我们在解说的过程中
While commentating
几乎把嘴都贴在话筒上
our lips are pressed against the mics
尽量让大家知道场上的情况
Doing our best to cover all actions on court.
1号扣球
No. 1 spikes!
好球
Great spike.
她扣的这个球确实有一股狠劲
That was one powerful spike.
帮助中国队夺回了发球权
With that China get the next serve.
这可能是她最后一届世界杯了
This is likely to be her last world cup.
球正好发在界内
The ball lands inbounds.
得分
A point!
日本队显然对临时 换上场的1号准备不足
Japan wasn't ready for China's No. 1 to play.
她彻底扭转了场上的局势
She is turning the game around!
赢了
We're winning.
中国队赢了
China wins a point!
我们看到教练的部署多么有效
Coach's tactic pays off!
中国队教练说
Coach said
中国队在今天比赛的目标
Team China's goal
就是一鼓作气 顽强到底
is to fight until the last minute
争取全胜
and take the Cup home.
1号属于兴奋型的球员
No. 1 is the kind of player who shines on court.
她鼓舞了大家
Her energy is contagious.
把场上中国队的气氛带活了
She gives the team an extra bounce.
日本队以为我们的主攻只会重扣
Japan thought our outside hitter only spikes
但她一改过去的高点强攻
but instead of her usual high and fierce attack
吊得出其不意
she used an unexpected tip against them.
中国队4比0领先
China leads at 4 nil.
像今天这种比赛场面我们也是很少见的
It's rare to see a match like this.
这些运动员她们在场上非常活跃
The players are all very active on court
好像身上藏了无穷无尽的力量
as if they have endless power.
日本队的教练员请求暂停
Japan's coach, calls for a timeout.
面对落后的局面 不知道他会有什么对策
Let's see how he is going to cope with the deficit.
听听周围的声音 请务必打起精神来
Hear the sounds around you. Please lift your spirits.
她们不可能永远保持那么好的状态
They couldn't play this well for long.
一定要跟上节奏
Must keep up the pace.
树里战术要大声喊出来
Call out the play.
是
Yes.
要像怪物一样大声
Like monsters!
是
Got it!
听好
Listen.
绝对不能输给中国队
We can't lose to China.
必胜
We must win.
我们最强
We are the best!
重新上场的日本队 受到了本队教练的感召
The Japanese rally again.
日本队跑动相当积极
They are running actively
迅速组织防守反击
and getting ready for a counterattack.
人们早就说过 日本队是打不死的
We've said that Japan is hard to kill.
只要比赛还没结束 她们就可能赢回来
As long as the game is on, they can win it back.
13比13
13 all.
日本队连续追分
Japan battles back to a tie.
中国女排再度陷入僵局
Team China is forced to stay passive again.
体力也出现了问题
Their stamina is going down as well.
在这紧要关头 中国队教练非常冷静
At this critical moment, Coach stays very calm.
为3号赢得了休息和调整的时间
He is gaining time for No. 3 to rest and adjust.
但不知道有腰伤的7号还能坚持吗
Is No. 7 able to push on with her hip injury?
你现在看看球场
Look at the court.
最年轻的是你
You are the youngest.
最有攻击力的也是你
And you have the strongest attack.
十八岁我把你招进了国家队
I called you up to the national team when you were 18.
对你训练这么苦 所有的一切
Everything I've put you through
都是为了今天
all leads up to today.
上场吧
Get ready.
有什么球尽管给我
Set every ball to me.
我负责砸过去
I will hit it over.
加油
Come on!
再不拼就没机会了
Fight, this is our chance!
加油
Come on, come on!
15比14 日本队领先
Japan takes the lead 15:14.
多么关键的时刻
What a crucial moment!
中国队 高点强攻
China's spiking from the top.
打中了
The ball's in!
中国的姑娘好样的
Good job girls!
队员们配合得真默契
Great teamwork!
中国队夺回了发球权
China gets to serve next.
四号位斜线扣球
A diagonal spike from Area 4.
真不容易
A hard-earned point.
15平
It's a tie at 15!
中国队拦网得分 16比15
China blocks and wins a point, 16:15!
中国队准确地预判了日本队的进攻线路
They successfully predicted Japan's tactics
把日本队的扣球拦死
and break their attack!
各位听众 各位观众
Everyone out there
台湾同胞港澳同胞 海外侨胞们
our fellow Chinese home and abroad
这是这届世界杯比赛 最后一场最后一局的比赛
this is the last game in the last match of this World Cup
这是对中国女排最后的一次考验了
and the final challenge for the national volleyball team.
中国队发球
China serves.
现在是由10号发球
No. 10 is serving.
日本队把球传起来
Japan receives.
现在传到四号位
The ball is set to Area 4.
日本队扣球
Japan spikes.
17比15
It's 17:15!
中国队胜利了
Victory for China!
为了这一刻
This is the moment
中国几代人苦苦等待了多少年
that generations of Chinese people have dreamed of!
队员们都抱在一起
The players are hugging each other.
中国队以七战七胜的成绩
China takes home the World Cup
夺得了第三届世界杯比赛的冠军
with 7 straight wins!
同志
Comrade
你是运动员吗
are you an athlete?
我也是打排球的
I'm a volleyball player.
你是打排球的
You play volleyball, too?
恭喜
Congratulations.
中国队很厉害
China has got a great team.
我一直努力尝试
I've been trying to reach
跳到你的摸高
your jumping height for so long.
但还没成功
I haven't made it.
你可能没有我跳得那么高
You may not have reached my height
但你打得比我好
but you're playing better.
你们更加有团队精神
Plus your team plays as one.
我背你上去
We'll piggyback you onto the stage.
没事 我自己来
I can do it.
别掉队 都跟上
Stay in line, don't fall behind.
别哭
Don't cry.
一
One
二
Two
三
Three
亲自来啊
In person?
压力是有 但
It's much pressure but
一定竭尽全力
we will give it our best.
节奏 不要忘了节奏
Rhythm, don't forget rhythm.
注意变化
Change it up!
我明白 明白
Got it.
轻装上阵
Don't think too much.
摆正位置拼对手
Focus on fighting the opponent.
好球
That's a good one.
什么好球
What good one?
你球点太早了 再接一个
You spike too early. One more!
拼起来 好
Come on, come on, good.
来 我问你 今天早上吃了什么
What did you eat today?
棉花糖吗
Marshmallow?
说了你跟美国队打 你扣的点那么低
If you spike so low against the Americans
你不跟打墙上一样吗
it'd be no difference from hitting a wall.
击球点要高
Spike at the highest point.
听到没有
Understand?
感谢领导关心
Thank you for checking in.
压力就是动力
The pressure is also great motivation.
郎导 什么指示
What can I do for you, Coach?
你这个习惯没有变
The old habit hasn't changed?
怎么样
How's it?
风是有点
There's a slight breeze...
影响不了发球
but it won't affect serves.
是吗
Yeah?
不过这比赛之前
To be honest
我们这样见面 老是觉得怪怪的
I feel weird meeting like this before a match.
三年前我去美国 当教练的时候 我问过你
3 years ago I asked you about taking over the US team.
你说你支持我
You told me that I had your support.
其实从那时候开始
Back then
你就应该知道
you should have known
我们早晚会碰到
that we'd meet like this sooner or later.
我们躲不掉的
We can't run from this.
这么重要的东西你怎么乱放
How could you have that lying around?
你又不懂英语
You don't know English.
我听力还行
My listening is okay.
我就阅读跟口语差点
Just need to work on my oral and reading.
好了 你约我出来想说啥
So, why did you ask me out?
你还记得教练常跟我们说
You remember what Coach used to tell us?
杯子为什么能盛水
Why can a glass hold water?
因为它是空的
Because it's empty.
那你觉得明天比赛谁会赢
Which team do you think will win tomorrow?
你那么多次带队打败过美国队
You've beaten the US team so many times.
论实力 美国打不过中国队
Abilities wise, team USA is no match for Team China.
郎平
Ping.
其实你担心的 不是明天美国队会输
But what you really think is not that the US will lose
而是会赢对吧
but they'd win, right?
我明白
I get it.
你想让我放松
You want us to relax
带着中国女排能打出状态来
and bring out our best.
我心里当然希望中国队赢
Of course I hope China can win.
但是作为职业教练
But as a coach
我有责任帮助美国队
Team USA is my responsibility.
我们都三十年的朋友了
We've been friends for 30 years.
你对女排的感情
Of course I know
我还不知道吗
your love for the Chinese team.
你放松吧
Relax.
明天尽全力打
Just give us your best shot.
这才是我们女排精神
That's the only way to honour our fighting spirit.
哪怕失去希望 每日最忙慢
You might have lost hope, wandering around...
无魂有体亲像稻草人
like a scarecrow without a soul.
人生可比是海上的波浪
Life is like the waves of the sea.
有时起有时落
There are highs and lows.
好运歹命
No matter good luck or bad luck
总吗要照起工来行
life needs to go on.
三分天注定
Three parts fate
七分靠打拼
seven parts hard work.
爱拼才会赢
Love the fight to win!
我唱得不好
I'm a bad singer.
但我喜欢这首歌
But I love this song.
《爱拼才会赢》
"Love the Fight to Win".
这些年
Over the years
光顾着训练了
I've been busy training
都没仔细看看
Never realise...
我们这些姑娘一个个的真漂亮
how beautiful you all are.
你们这些年怎么走到今天
How all of you came to be here.
每一次训练
Every training
每一次受伤 每一次跌倒
every injury and fall
我全部都看在眼里面
I've witnessed them all.
看着你们
Looking at you
我想起我当年进排球队
I remember when I first entered the volleyball team.
看到的那些姑娘们
And the women there.
你们真像她们
You are just like them.
这些年你们对得起自己
You should be proud of yourselves.
我从心里面感谢你们
I'm deeply grateful to all of you.
好了
Okay
别再看着我了
stop staring at me.
再看我要哭了
I'm gonna cry.
不练了
Today's practice is over.
回去吃上三块巧克力
Eat three blocks of chocolate
明天3比0我们讨个好彩头 好吧
for each set you'll win tomorrow! Okay?
好 来
Yeah! Come!
加油
Fight!
刚才几个点特别好
The last few points were very good.
姑娘们
Girls, listen.
接下来美国队一定会 重点加强破坏我们的一传
Next, they'll try to disrupt our first pass.
她们开始慌了 持续施压
They're getting nervous, stay on top of them.
要提前预判
Move early.
破坏她们的一传
Make it difficult for them on the receive.
加强拦网
Block, faster!
五号位尤其要注意
Pay attention to Area 5.
五号位
Area 5!
破坏她们节奏
Don't give them time to think.
一传
First pass!
注意四号位 从三号位进攻
Watch the outside. Go for the middle.
强攻的时候 其他人加强保护
Protect when making strong attacks.
点高
High point!
再来
Again.
打短球 短球
Hit it short, short!
不要慌
No rush.
我都没慌你们在慌什么
I'm not in a hurry, why are you?
这是她们的弱轮
It's the weaker rotation
把握拦网时机
time your blocks.
动脑子
Think.
给她们压力
Put pressure on them.
多吊球
Tip more.
洛根 小心她们吊球
Hey Logan, watch out for their tips
加强保护
Protection!
她要吊球
She's going for the tip!
五星红旗迎风飘扬 胜利歌声多么响亮
Our red flag flies as the song of victory echoes in the sky
好 现在听我说
Alright, listen to me...
她们的1号 体力下降
Their No. 1 is tired.
中国队会重点在 二号位 三号位发动进攻
Focus on Areas 2 and 3.
注意力集中
Concentrate!
加强拦网
Make strong blocks.
盯死
Mark them.
歌唱我们亲爱的祖国
Let's sing for our dear motherland.
坚持给我挺住
Hold on for me.
你没问题的 肯定没问题
You can do this, definitely can.
格拉斯
Kim.
但是要变一下 打短球 打直线
Make changes on attack, hit it straight and short.
有
Yes sir.
中午吃的什么
What did you eat today?
牛排
Steak.
非常好 上去给我整
Very good, show me what you've got.
拦死1号
No. 1, block her.
这都什么表情
What's with the look on your face?
不用想那么多了
Don't think too much about it.
现在我们该做什么
What we should do now
该做的是 一分一分给我把球咬回来
is to fight back point by point!
球可以输
We can lose to our opponent
人不能输
but not to ourselves.
我没什么可说的了
I've got nothing to say.
这是你们自己的比赛
This is your game.
拼了 不拼没机会了
Fight, this is our last chance!
美国队 一 二 三
USA! One, two, three.
一 二 加油
One, two, come on!
美国队
USA!
现在是第五局的比赛
The match has come to the 5th set.
美国队拿到了赛点
Match point for Team USA.
美国队一传没有到位
Their first pass is bad.
美国队调整进攻 这是3号
US adjusts their attack. This is No. 3.
中国队还有机会
China still has the chance.
美国队拦网成功
US blocks to win the point.
15比11
15:11.
这样 美国胜了第五局
Team USA wins the 5th set.
美国女子排球队以3比2战胜了中国队
With that, they win the match 3:2.
中国队和美国队实力相当
China and the US are well-matched teams.
但是今天的中国女排欠缺了一点运气
Today China was just short of luck.
可能是主场压力影响了球队的发挥
Home pressure may have affected their performance.
虽然输了
Despite the loss
但中国队也拼到了最后
they made it to the end.
我们不以输赢论英雄
They are all heroes.
希望中国女排调整好状态
Let's hope they can adjust
迎接下面的比赛
and do better in coming matches.
每次碰到郎指导的祖国球队
Playing Coach Jenny's home team
我们想证明我们才是最棒的
we wanted to show that we are the best.
今天我们做到了
Today we did that!
我们做到了
We did it!
至少我儿子开心了
At least my son is happy.
终于能见到我了
I can finally go home.
中国队输了
China lost.
他们连骂都只是骂你
And all they do is blame you.
妈
Mom!
恭喜你 你们太棒了
Congratulations. You were so great.
我以前只知道你是教排球的
I only knew you coached volleyball.
妈 我真的好开心
Mom, I'm so happy!
你开心吗
Are you happy?
开心
Yeah.
我为你骄傲
I'm really proud of you.
浪浪
Lydia.
你很久没回中国了
It's been a long time since you've been to China.
这儿变化很大
It's changed so much.
很多地方我都不认识了
I no longer recognise some of the places.
妈 你是在哭吗
Mom, are you crying?
我刚刚碰到了一位我很久不见的老朋友
I saw a friend I hadn't seen for a long time.
我们在一块儿聊了很久
We talked for a while.
也许
I probably
今天我让他失望了
disappointed him today.
对不起
I'm sorry.
女士
Excuse me lady?
你知道我有权 把你的车从残疾人停车位拖走
You know I can have you towed for parking in a handicap spot.
非常抱歉 女士
Oh, sorry.
你看起来还没到使用它的年纪
You look too young to need this.
二十年的运动伤带给我的
20 years of being an athlete.
什么运动
Oh? What sport?
排球
Volleyball.
排球怎么可能把你弄成这样
How the hell do you injure yourself playing volleyball?
我跟你一样有时也会感到困惑
Sometimes, it puzzles me too.
现在 连日本队都打不过了
Now they can't even beat Japan.
真是一代不如一代了
Each generation is worse than the last.
什么玩意 干脆解散算了
What is this? They should just dismiss this team.
这都什么年代了 你至于生气吗
It's not the 80s, don't get so involved.
体育赛事就是游戏
Volleyball is just a game.
1981年世界杯
In 1981's Volleyball World Cup
她顶着腰伤坚持比赛的精神
she finished the match despite a hip injury.
感动了一代人
Her fighting spirit inspired a whole generation.
今年过年时
After the new year
她的病情急剧恶化
her conditions deteriorated.
因癌症医治无效
Defeated by cancer,
于2013年4月1日在北京逝世
she passed away on April 1st, 2013 in Beijing.
别掉队 都跟上
Stay in line, don't fall behind.
别哭
Don't cry.
我的比赛就要打完了
My match is nearly over.
我先下场休息
I'm going to take a break.
来世我们还做队友
Let's be teammates again in our next life.
遗体送别仪式 现在开始
The service begins.
请全体肃立
Please all rise.
我们相信你能给中国女排带来新东西
You can bring something new to the women's team.
我们大家都支持你
You have our support.
回来吧
Come back.
挺好的
How you've been?
挺好
Fine.
妈 你快回来了吧
Mom, you'll be home soon?
浪浪
Lydia
我可能下周回不去美国了
I might not come back next week.
请问是郎导吗
Is Lang Ping the new head coach?
可以说几句吗
Please say something.
请您留下拍照好吗
Can you stay for some photos?
郎导
Coach Lang!
请问您有什么话要说吗
Please say something!
是郎平
It's Lang Ping.
众望所归
As we had hoped
她成为了中国女排新任主教练
she's the new head coach of Women's Volleyball Team.
我还是那句话
I'm sticking to what I said
不要对目前的中国女排提过高的要求
we shouldn't have too much expectations on the current team.
中国女排现在在世界上就是第二集团
The Women's Team is just second-rated.
这是现实
That's the reality.
现在的年轻人
The players we have
和八十年代的老女排没法比
are much worse comparing to the ones in the 80s.
我认为必须要加强日常管理
I suggest we manage them on a daily basis
抓作风
Be firm.
手机该交的一定要交
Take away their phones if needed.
郎导
Coach Lang
我是从小看着您打球长大的
I watched you play since I was a kid.
我当然能明白您着眼于未来的想法
I understand you're looking towards the future
但我建议
but I suggest
国家队还是稳一稳 先过渡
we should stabilise the team as a stop gap.
不好意思
I'm sorry
今天这个会呢
I'm here in this meeting
不只是我坐在这儿听你们说
not to listen to what you have to say
我也希望大家能听我说
but for you all to hear me out.
要改变中国女排的现状 不能只靠哪一个人
Changing the team is not a one person job.
包括我在内
Me included.
国家队的训练方法是三十年前制定的
Our sporting system was set 30 years ago.
跟不上国际潮流了
It's outdated.
现在中国女排只有一条路可走
There's only one way to go
改革
reform.
下面我来宣布国家队的三项改革计划
Now I will announce my 3 reform plans:
首先我会推行当今国际通用的
I will start by doing what other international teams do.
大国家队模式
Choose from a bigger squad.
以前国家队是十二个人
Where we used to have 12 players
打主力的只有六七个
with 6 or 7 good enough to start
现在我可能选三十个人
now I'm going to pick 30 players.
那个女孩叫什么名字
Who's that kid with long hair?
她不应该打沙排
She shouldn't play beach volleyball.
应该打室内
She should play indoor.
这个是张常宁
Her name is Zhang Changning.
她转室内的申请已经被批准了
She just got permission to transfer to indoor volleyball.
今天是她最后一场沙排比赛
This is her last beach volleyball match.
4号惠若琪 她从小到大的偶像都是你
No. 4 Hui Ruoqi. You're her idol since childhood.
那肯定没问题
Then she should be good.
辽宁队这个二传叫
Who's the setter for Liaoning?
叫丁霞
Ding Xia.
她一个传球的 最好的一项
As a setter, her best attribute is
是扣球
spiking.
我去
Shit!
好球
Good one.
三十个如果不够
If 30 is not enough
就选五十个
we select 50.
老东西
Old lady!
你以为宿舍你家的
This is a dorm, not your home.
- 你有病啊 - 要是五十个还不够
- You're out of your mind! - If 50 is not enough
那就一百个
then 100.
郎导
Coach Lang
我不同意您的观点
I beg to differ.
我们五连冠时期
Back from your championship days
不也是六七个队员
it was always about training 6 or 7 players
长期地在一起像一家人一样的训练磨合
together for a long period of time, like a family.
所以才能打遍全世界
That's how we become world beaters.
五连冠
The winning days
1986年
were in 1986.
二十七年了
27 years ago.
郎导
Coach
您看这个5号
see this No. 5
叫朱婷
her name is Zhu Ting.
94年出生
Born in 1994.
身高一米九四
1.94m tall.
这个河南5号我见过
I've seen this No. 5 of Henan before.
这个朱婷虽然身高不错
Zhu Ting's is quite tall
但是身子薄 打球软
but she's thin, so her spikes are weak.
扣球也只会扣斜线
And she only spikes diagonals.
队里打算把她调到二队去
We're thinking putting her to the backup team.
郎导 您看那个3号不错
Coach, that No. 3 is quite good.
原地起跳都敢扣
She can spike without a run up.
这5号以后不得了
That's truly something.
报到
I'm here.
陈鹿
Chen Lu.
迟到半个小时
30 minutes late.
十圈场地跑 五十个俯卧撑
10 laps, 50 pushups.
什么时候叫你停你再停
I'll tell you when to stop.
慢点跳起来 慢一点
Jump later. Slow down!
给保护
Protection!
漂亮
Nice one!
起了
Up!
背后球
When you back set
控制传球的这个节奏
watch the rhythm
传球手型
and your hand.
背后球别不敢给
Don't be scared for a back set.
噢
Fine.
就是个队长
You're the captain
又不是教练
not the coach.
你把这么多队员都招进来
With a large number of new recruits in the team
新队员和老队员之间的矛盾
the conflicts between players of different ages.
你怎么解决
How would you deal with it?
行
Fine!
那我今天就挑明了说
I'm putting it out here right now.
我觉得队里就是因为你们老队员太抱团
You older players like to stay among yourselves
看我们新来的怎么都不顺眼
nitpicking at everything we newcomers do.
有错不能说
Not even when you're wrong?
中国女排是什么你知道吗
Do you know what it means to be on this team?
就是
I agree.
你们也太自我了吧
You all are too self-centred
还这么不尊重老队员
and there are no respects.
动不动就摸人屁股
Who'd just slap someone on the ass.
我们以前哪敢这么做
We wouldn't dare to do that.
原来国家队就是听别人教训的
I didn't know being here is about taking lessons from you.
我觉得这个旗太大我扛不动
This is too much for me.
大不了走人吧
I might as well just leave.
丁霞你说话过脑子吗
Ding Xia, do you think before you speak?
我告诉你全队都等你呢
The whole team is waiting for you.
张常宁
Zhang Changning!
干吗呢
What are you waiting for?
打沙排转沙子呢
It's not beach volleyball, there's no sand.
我的第二项计划
My second reform plan:
在全球聘请教练
Hiring coaches around the world
搭建一个复合型的教练团队
building a coaching team.
这怎么能行呢
This won't work.
我们中国女排从来没用过老外
We've never had foreigners in the coaching team.
从今天开始
From this day forward
有了
we will.
你停一下
Stop, put it down.
朱婷
Ting
你现在体重过低
you're underweight.
会受伤
You'll get injured.
给你申请的蛋白粉
This is for you. Protein powder.
增长肌肉
To increase your muscle mass.
好好吃饭 注意休息
Eat more and take good rest.
郎导 这个多少钱
Coach, how much is this?
那得多少经费
That sounds expensive.
第三项计划
My third change:
大国家队时代
in a bigger squad system
不分主力和替补
I'll scrap starters and backups.
只有首发和非首发
There'll only be first team and second team.
目前这支中国女排
In this China women's national team,
感觉谁都是主力 谁也都是替补
it seems like everyone can start with this new set up.
本次比赛 郎平换人已达二十六次之多
Ping has made 26 substitutions since the match began.
今天的中国女排 只有一个主角
The centre of the national team nowadays
不是场上的队员
are not the players
而是站在场边的郎平
but Lang Ping.
有了首发和非首发的轮换机制
With the first and second team system
我们就可以采用不同的阵容
we can use different lineups and tactics
在大赛中应对不同的对手
according to our opponents in competitions.
另外 我也会告诉我的队员
Also, I'll tell my players
排球是我们的工作
that volleyball is our job.
但不是我们生命的全部
Not our whole life.
好了
That's it.
今天就练到这吧
No more session today.
休息
Take a break.
去谈恋爱吧
Go on a date.
郎导 我们都没对象
Coach, we don't have anyone to date.
我们事业心都比较重
We're all dedicated athletes.
拿不到冠军不好意思谈恋爱
We're not going to date before becoming world champions.
你们这是球筐吗 真能装
Drop the act, guys.
好了 那我改变主意了
Because I can always change my mind.
跑
Run!
我希望我的队员将来
I hope our players
不只是一位优秀的运动员
aren't only the best athletes
还是一个优秀的人
but also the best human beings.
我的话讲完了
That's all I've got to say.
有点复杂
Sounds complicated.
听得我血压都高了
Make my blood pressure rise.
你怎么看
What do you think?
我赞同
I agree to the proposal.
大家的意见都听到了
We've heard everything.
郎导
Coach Lang
体育总局会全力支持你的改革计划
we will make these reforms.
填好了交给我
Hand the questionnaire in when you finish.
谢谢郎导
Thanks Coach.
你的性格是什么 家庭背景
What's your personality? Background?
你的技术特点是什么
What's your playing style?
你为什么打排球
Why do you play volleyball?
你的爱好
Your interests?
未来目标
Future goals?
郎导拿错了
Coach, there's a mistake!
我怎么拿的丽姐的问卷
Mine says Yunli.
你们不是室友吗
Aren't you guys roommates?
你们就是答对方的问卷
You can only fill in the other person's.
都有了
You all got one?
互相看看
Make sure you have it.
丽姐
Yunli
我们俩把问卷换过来吧
why don't we swap and answer?
那不行
No.
你是不是对我们九零后有什么意见
Yunli, you have a thing against we post-90s?
要不这样吧
Well.
我俩玩一个游戏
Let's play a game.
我心里想着一个人 你猜是谁
You take a guess at who I'm thinking of.
我只能回答你是或者不是
I can only answer yes or no.
打排球的吗
Volleyball player?
是
Yes.
女的
Is it a she?
是
Yes.
是郎导吗
Coach Lang?
对
Yes.
我现在心里也想着一个人
I've got someone too.
是你自己
You.
你怎么知道的
How did you know?
这就是你们九零后和我们的区别
That's the difference between us.
我要站在场上 我要打排球
I want to stay on the court and play volleyball!
试试
Try it.
我们是集体项目
We are a team
你得喊出来
and you need to shout.
你喊出来才能释放出来
You need to let it out.
你啊
Ting
得知道自己为什么打球
you need to know why you play volleyball.
我之前去篮球队的时候
I was in basketball team before
篮球队说
and they told me
我太薄了
you're too skinny.
去皮划艇 说
Then the rowing team told me
闺女
kid
你这个腿往哪搁啊
where are you going to put your long legs?
所以
That's why
选了排球
I chose volleyball.
今天中国女排对阵土耳其女排
Today Team China is playing Team Turkey.
郎平首发了9号张常宁
Coach Lang has sent in No. 9 Zhang Changning.
我们看到她习惯性地转了十几圈球
Still can't quit the habit of spinning the ball.
裁判哨响了 发球超时
The referee whistles for serve time violation.
本届世界女排大奖赛
At the Volleyball World Grand Prix
中国队出乎意料输给土耳其队
China is upset by Turkey
无缘下一轮比赛
and misses out on the next round.
在亚锦赛输给泰国队之后
After losing to Thailand
郎平的球队
Lang Ping's team
取得了三十八年以来
had the worst results
历史最差的成绩
for the national team in 38 years.
打得好
Well played.
请您评论一下今天中国队的表现吧
What do you think of your team's performance?
今天打得特别好
Today, they're good.
这个阵容攻击性够了
Our team is good at attacking.
我非常满意
I'm very happy with them.
郎导
Coach Lang
试了十四个阵容 输了十三场
we've tried 14 lineups and lost 13 matches.
还要试吗
Should we keep trying?
还可以再输
We can lose some more.
今天的比赛证明
Today's match proved that
中国女排与世界强队意大利女排
Italy, comparing to China
根本不是一个档次的球队
plays on another level.
现在 留给郎平的时间不多了
The time will soon be up for Ping.
郎导 您好
Coach Lang
我们这场打得这么难堪
it was quite an embarrassing match for China.
您考虑过换个战术吗
Have you thought about changing the tactics?
我就不知道你们是怎么混进国家队的
How did you make it into the national team?
对
Oh yeah
我把你们招来的
I picked you.
答卷我都看了
I've read your questionnaires.
里面有一条
There's 1 question
是问大家你们爱排球吗
"Do you love volleyball?"
几乎没有人回答
A lot of you left the answer blank.
我今天还得问一句
So I'm asking all of you one more time.
每个人都得回答
You all have to answer it.
你们爱排球吗
Do you love volleyball?
陈鹿
Lu?
郎导
Coach
我不爱
I don't.
我不想打球了
I don't want to play volleyball anymore.
从来没有一个人问过我
No one has ever asked me
是不是真的爱排球
if I really love volleyball.
您是第一个
You're the first.
我觉得
I think
人生不只是打排球拿冠军这一条路
life is not just about being a volleyball champion.
我想走我自己的路
I have to find my own way.
谢谢您 郎导
Thank you, Coach.
我准备要去考大学了
I'm going to apply for colleges.
日前中国女排爆出队史上 第一次有人主动离开
We've heard an athlete has quit the volleyball team.
郎平又接连让两名主力队员离队
Ping firing a number of starters from the squad.
外界哗然
Everyone is shocked.
有球迷认为郎平已经失去理智
Some fans think Ping has lost her mind.
面对各方质疑
Facing questions from all sides.
下面我宣布里约奥运会参赛运动员名单
I'm going to announce the squad for the Rio Olympics.
惠若琪
Hui Ruoqi.
张常宁
Zhang Changning.
刘晓彤
Liu Xiaotong.
朱婷
Zhu Ting.
徐云丽
Xu Yunli.
袁心玥
Yuan Xinyue.
颜妮
Yan Ni.
丁霞
Ding Xia.
魏秋月
Wei Qiuyue.
林莉
Lin Li.
龚翔宇
Gong Xiangyu.
好了 解散吧
That's all for today.
我这半年每天都练十个小时以上
I've trained 10 hours per day for the last 6 months
我就是为了在场上能够跳得更高一点
Just to jump that little bit higher on court.
我现在状态这么好
I'm in good form.
我真的不理解为什么是我不去
I don't understand why I'm not going.
就是因为你打得太好了
Because you've been playing too well.
对方把你摸得透透的
Our opponents have sussed you out.
春蕾
Chunlei
对不起
I'm sorry.
我是老队员 我理解
I'm an experienced player, I get it.
也接受
I accept your decision.
但是郎导一个运动员能有几个四年
But how many 4 years does an athlete have?
这是第一次有人主动离开国家队
The first person in history to walk out on the team.
你的心情我们能理解
We understand how you feel.
但是也不能因为这个 再让两位有经验的主力队员离队开
But you can't just let go two of the starting players.
这不是自断我们的手脚吗
That's self-destruction.
这就是战略战术问题了
It was a strategic decision.
如果你们想听 我可以给你们讲五个小时
I could talk about it for hours if you'd like to listen.
不管怎么样
No matter what
我们大家是支持你的
we give you our full support.
包括
Including
一位著名教练
a renown coach.
因为当时
Back then
他也是主动退出竞选来支持你的
he withdrew from the head coach selection to support you.
我认为郎平
I think Coach Lang...
应该是中国女排最佳的主教练人选
is the best fit for the role.
我放弃竞选
I withdraw.
以目前国家队的阵容
We think that with your current players
去打国际女排联赛
attending the International Volleyball League
不论是从外部形象还是队内的士气
will harm the morale and image.
都将产生不良的负面影响
And have a negative effect on the team.
所以 我们这次建议 国家青年队去打这个比赛
So we will recommend the national youth team to go instead.
输了 无所谓
It's okay if they lose.
也给你留出时间调整队伍
This way your team can have more time to adjust.
喂 郎导
Yes, Coach?
亚文
Yawen
把中青队全体队员全部调到国家队来
Transfer everyone in the youth team to the national team.
收到
Copy that.
好了
Well.
她们去不了了
The youth team can't go anymore.
郎平
Lang Ping
你如果这么搞
if this is how you want to do this
你要想清楚
just be very clear
你对女排能不能负得起这个责
what the consequences could be!
大晚上的 健身呢
Working out late?
你不是说
Didn't you say
当今的排球应该是快乐的
that volleyball is supposed to be a joy?
你这样天天跟所有人对立 你快乐吗
Do you feel joy making everyone go against you?
杯子为什么能装水
Why can a glass hold water?
因为它是空的
Because it's empty.
你今天来要是说服我的话
If you are here to change my mind
那你就回去转告他们
you go tell the experts
我郎平 今天就是一意孤行了
I'm going to do this my way.
你不用孤行
You're not alone.
别管专家怎么说
Despite what the experts say
领导是支持你的
you have the Administration's support.
你为什么退出主教练的竞选 为什么
Why did you withdraw from the election?
给我让贤
So that I could win?
我不需要
I don't need that.
你以为我心甘
You think I wanted to withdraw?
我承认我土
Yes, I'm old-fashioned
我不懂英文
I don't speak English
我没出国待过
never lived abroad
我没有国际视野
and I don't have international horizon.
你以为我不想带女排再拿几次世界冠军
But I wanted to win more world championships as the head coach.
可是他们不信
But no one believes it's possible.
他们说我们永远高不过俄罗斯
They say that we will never be taller than the Russians
也跳不过巴西
jump higher than the Brazilians
也没有塞尔维亚跟意大利的力量
stronger than the Serbians and Italians.
有人还过来跟我说
Some even said to me
现在时代变了
time has changed.
中国人现在已经不需要女排了
Chinese people today don't need women's volleyball.
以前我们还有精神
The 80s team at least had the fighting spirit.
现在连起码那点精神都没了
The new team has nothing.
有的人还说
Some even say
拿了世界冠军又怎么样
even if we were world champions again
大家还会像以前一样 跑到街上又哭又笑 又叫又跳吗
will people still celebrate on the streets?
不会了
Not any more.
因为你是郎平
Because you are Lang Ping
都相信你会给中国女排带来暂时的希望
only you can bring hope for the moment.
暂时的希望
For the moment?
如果我的出现
If they think I'm here
只给大家带来暂时的希望
only to give them hope for the moment
他们就想错了
then they are wrong.
我郎平从来不装
I don't put on acts
我都是玩真格的
I am what I act.
别人说你这样
Some would tell you
还不如回北京队
it's better to go back to Beijing.
总比在这里只有到了晚上 才敢偷偷练球得好
Better than staying here and sneaking in to practice at night.
回地方队能拿世界冠军吗
Can I win the world championship there?
鹰有时候也会掉在地上
Eagles have to land every so often
但鸡 永远飞不了鹰那么高
but chickens will never fly as high as the eagles.
你说谁是鸡
Who do you call a chicken?
宝宝
Changning
五秒钟之内你把那沙子给我转完
I need you to shake off all the sand in 5 seconds.
快来
Come on!
魏秋
Qiuyue
给你个气球好吧
you need a balloon?
手太软
Your hands are too soft.
小惠
Ruoqi
你是拦网 不是漏斗
you need to block not like a leaking hole.
丁霞 少说话
Xia, less talking.
精力集中
Stay focus.
再来
Let's go again.
为什么在答卷上写着
Why did you answer on the questionnaire
你打球是为了你爸妈
you're playing volleyball for your family?
我爸妈都是农民
My parents are farmers.
上面有姐姐 下面又是妹妹
I have elder and younger sisters.
家庭负担挺大的
My parents were under a lot of pressure.
平时爸爸会修车
My dad also takes side jobs like fixing bikes.
有时候看见爸爸修车修不动的时候
Every time I saw him too exhausted to continue working
我确实想
I wanted to
退出排球
quit volleyball.
说想去
Then
广东打工
get a job in Guangdong.
但是
But
我爸爸说
my father said
我们农村的想出来
the quickest way
搞体育还是最快的
to success for us villagers is sports.
练体育是苦
Sports is hard
但生活才是难
but the real difficulty is life.
哪怕是砸锅卖铁
Even if he needed to pawn our valuables
他也支持我
he'd support me.
你知道吗
You know
其实我第一眼看到你的时候
the first time I saw you
我就觉得我们俩特别像
you reminded me of my younger self.
加油
Come on.
加油 朱
Come on, Ting.
来
One more.
加油 朱
Come on, Ting.
朱婷
Zhu Ting
喊出来
Give me some noise.
你不喊出来 你就打不出来
There's no power without your voice.
再来
Again!
喊出来
Where is it?
喊啊
Your voice!
别打了 坐那儿
Stop and sit down.
今天不练了
Enough for today.
你这球打成这样
You play like this
你对得起你爸妈吗
can you look into your parents' eyes?
回去打工去吧
Go and find a regular job.
别在这儿了
You don't need to be here.
朱婷
Zhu Ting
不管你是城市的还是农村的
whether you're from the city or from a village
在我这儿都一样
I treat all of you the same.
农村是你的出身
A village is where you're from
别拿来说故事
not a story you tell people.
你要是打不出来
If you can't play well
你回去打工
try to find normal work
人家都嫌你高
they'll think you're a freak.
别说了
Stop it!
这劲还不错
You've found your voice.
再来
Come on.
朱婷
Ting
我问你
tell me
为什么打球
why do you play volleyball?
回答我
Answer me.
为我爸妈
For my parents.
那你永远也打不出来
Then you'll never hit the top.
再想
Give me something.
为什么
Why do you play?
为我自己
For myself!
那你自己要什么
And what do you want?
成为你
To be like you!
满意了
You happy!
那你就搞错了
I think you've misunderstood me.
你永远也不会成为我
You'll never be me.
我说你跟我以前很像
When I said you were like me
是因为我以前做替补的时候
I meant you were like when I was a backup
打球打得太烂了
and played really bad.
跟你现在一样
Same as you are now.
不知道为什么打球是吧
You ladies don't know why you play volleyball?
那今天晚上就全睡这
Spend a night here.
好好想想
Think about it.
集体露营呢
Group camping?
怎么了
What's wrong?
这么看来 郎导带你们来这里是对了
Coach Lang made the right decision to bring you here.
我以前一到心里面没力气的时候 就喜欢来这里
In the past, whenever I was in low-spirit, I came here.
来了以后 对着墙一阵猛扣
I spiked hard against this old wall.
然后这心里面马上就有力气了
And my heart would be filled with hope again.
就这么神奇 不信
You don't believe it?
不信起来试试
Have a go.
反正也睡不着 来
You're not sleeping anyway.
试试
Try it.
看到没有
Look.
这墙上的每一个球印
All the dents on the wall
就是以前那帮老女排
are left by those girls
一个球一个球给凿出来的
hitting balls into the wall over and over again.
看到吗
Look
这个郎平的
This is Lang Ping's.
那时候我们打球 那真的是什么都没有
Back then, we had none of the resources you have.
但我们心里面有这个
But we had this in here.
现在你们什么都有了
Now you have everything.
但是不是有的时候
But sometimes
这个找不到了
you lose this.
来 一起 都一起
Come, all together.
反正也睡不着 来
You're not sleeping.
小时候 我就在这个球场
Coach Lang and I used to come here.
陪着郎导
I was with her training
拚命地死练
day in, day out.
郎导的身体你们是很清楚的
You know she's not in good physical condition.
从脖子往下没有一块骨头是好的
Volleyball has broken every bone below her neck.
那她为什么还回来陪着你们死磕
But why is she still here, fighting alongside you guys?
就是因为心里面的这个东西
Because she has this inside.
这个东西是什么
What is this?
就是女排精神
It's the team's fighting spirit.
是我们的国家
It's our country.
继续
Go on.
用力
Harder!
再用力 喊出来
Harder, give me some noise!
喊出来
Where's your voice?
大声 姑娘们
Girls! Voice!
喊出来
Your voice!
记着吗
Remember?
还记得三十年前我们在这里喝了杯咖啡
30 years ago, you and I had coffee here
出去比赛就赢了
and the team came back winners.
讨个好彩头
Drink it up for good luck.
苦也得喝了它
I know it's bitter, but you have to finish it.
要不然我输了怨你
I'll blame it on you if we lose.
行
Fine.
但我知道 巴西队这次在主场的压力
I know how Brazil feels, fighting on home turf.
肯定比福建的十二级台风还强
It's more terrifying than the scale 12 typhoon in Fujian.
以前我们打比赛
When I was still a player
老是背着个大包袱
we played with so much baggage.
成天就说拿冠军 拿冠军
We focused too much on winning
拿了亚军都算失败
even second-place was not good enough.
我现在不这么想
I won't be thinking like that anymore.
我这次就要轻轻松松地去打这个比赛
I will treat this one like any other match.
放心吧
Don't worry.
放心
Of course.
我当然要放心 我要不放心
I won't worry about you.
我当时能退出竞选吗
If I didn't, I wouldn't have withdrawn from the election.
我从心里面觉得你
I truly believe that you
才能带给女排新的东西
are the one who can bring something new to the team.
我是安安静静死在家里边那个人
While I die quietly at home
但你绝对是轰轰烈烈死在球场上那个人
you will die gallantly on a volleyball court.
我这要上飞机了 说点吉利的
Say something lucky! I'm about to take off.
好 对
Haha, yes.
吉利
Good luck.
我不管别人还需不需要中国女排
I don't care if others need the women's volleyball team.
我需要
But I do.
明白
Gotcha.
2016里约奥运会女排小组赛
It's the 2016 Rio Olympics.
中国女排接连输给荷兰 塞尔维亚和美国队
China women's volleyball has lost to the Netherlands, Serbia and the USA.
仅以第四名的成绩勉强挤进淘汰赛
They came fourth and squeezed into the quarter-finals
即将遭遇世界排名第一的东道主巴西队
where they'll meet the host and reigning Olympic champion Brazil.
自08年以来 两队的交手纪录
The win-lost record of the two teams is 18:1 since 2008
巴西队以18比1 占据绝对优势
with Brazil holding an absolute advantage.
外界普遍认为 两支球队的实力根本不在一个水平
Many think that Brazil is on another level to China.
郎平率领的中国队 将在这场比赛后直接回家
The Chinese team, led by Lang Ping, is likely to go home after the match.
今天先不练了
No training today.
回去休息
Take a good rest.
明天是淘汰赛
Tomorrow is the elimination match
输了就卷铺盖走人
we go home if we lose.
我刚才看见赖导在查回去的机票了
I saw Coach Lai looking at flights just now.
我们打这么差 郎导就不该带我们来
We've been playing badly. Coach Lang shouldn't have taken us here.
我们明天只有两条路
We're got 2 options:
要么放下一切 轻装上阵
We leave everything behind and fight on court
要么畏手畏脚 死路一条
or be a nervous wreck and lose before the fight.
我刚刚掐指一算
I've figured it out.
明天
Tomorrow
3比1 我们稳赢
we'll win 3:1.
我觉得我们上场比赛没有输
We only lost the last match
输是因为比赛只能打五局
because there are only 5 sets.
再来两局 准赢
If we play to 7, we will surely win.
你好
Hello?
我们要关门了 你出去的时候能锁上门吗
We are closing. Can you lock the door on your way out?
好的 谢谢
Alright, thank you.
是我太紧张了
I got nervous.
我以为我走遍了整个世界
I thought I've had enough experience
我已经是一个职业的体育人了
to call myself a sports professional.
原来不是
Turns out I'm not.
曾经一位外国记者问我
A foreign reporter once asked me
你们中国人
why do Chinese
为什么这么看重一场排球比赛的输赢呢
take winning a match so seriously?
我说
I said
因为我们的内心还不够强大
because we're not strong enough inside.
等有一天我们的内心强大了
When we have true inner strength
我们就不会把赢
winning will no longer be
作为比赛的唯一的价值
a match's only value.
我们这代人是苦过来的
Our generation went through a lot of hardship.
做什么事情
Whatever we do
身上都背着沉重的包袱
we carry a heavy burden with us.
我的医生跟我说
My doctor told me
你是六十岁的心脏
I have the heart of a sixty-year-old
八十岁的骨头
and the body of an eighty-year-old.
我姐跟我说
My sister asked me
你能不能
if I could
给我们留半条命
save half a life for the family.
其实
The truth is
我就是放不下
I can't let go.
我放不下你们
I can't let go of you.
放不下排球
I can't let go of volleyball.
我有责任帮助你们
I feel I have the responsibility to help you
好好地享受体育的本身
to enjoy the sports itself.
开心地去打球
And enjoy volleyball.
姑娘们
Ladies
明天要比赛了
tomorrow is the big match.
过去的包袱 由我们这代人来背
The burden of the past should be carried by my generation.
你们应该打出你们自己的排球
Fight it your own way.
你们应该振作起来
You should keep your heads up
放心地去打
without worries
放开了打 豁出去打
relax and give it all you've got.
我和你们在一起
I'm always by your side.
加油
Come on!
第一局我们可能会打得比较困难
The first game today will be very difficult
但是没关系
but it's okay.
瞧巴西队这股劲
Look how fired up they are.
她们肯定是想3比0拿下我们
They're only ready for 3 sets.
但是我们这几年的训练已经做好了准备
But I've prepared for this day.
拖住她们
Hang on
只要我们能把比赛坚持到第五局
and if we make it to 5th set
我们就有机会
we have a chance to win.
加油
Come on!
一 二 加油
One, two, fight!
这不是乒乓
This is not ping-pong.
回家吧 中国队
Go home China.
现在是2016年里约奥运会
It's the 2016 Rio Olympics women's volleyball match
中国女排对阵巴西女排
between China and Brazil.
巴西队是世界第一 又是东道主
Brazil is currently world No. 1 and playing at home.
大家不知道这个场地里 巴西球迷的声音有多大
You can imagine how loud the cheering is in the stadium.
08年以来 两队交手纪录
In terms of win-lost record since 2008
巴西队以18胜1负 占据了绝对优势
Brazil has got an absolute upper hand.
外界预测 这是中国队 在本届奥运会的最后一场比赛
Many predict this to be China's farewell match at Rio.
没关系
It's okay.
把一传接好
Concentrate on the receives.
我想今天中国队 只要打出自己正常的水平
I think as long as China plays up to par
无论比赛结果如何
the fans will accept and understand
球迷们还是会理解和接受
whatever the result is.
巴西队扣球得分
Brazil blocks to win the point.
加强保护
More protection!
巴西队二号位扣球得分
Brazil spikes a point from Area 2.
确实厉害
A world-beating team indeed.
中国队开局不利
Not a good start for China.
巴西队整体实力确实在我们之上
Brazil is definitely a stronger team
每个队员都很全面
with well-rounded players.
只要我们给她施压
If we keep pressing in...
对方发球冲击的效果非常凶猛
Their serves are very powerful
我们的一传环节不理想 很被动
leaving our first passes misplaced, we are too passive.
巴西队拥有全世界最强的两个副攻
With the world's 2 best blockers
在网口上拥有绝对的实力
Brazil has full control over the net.
第一局她们打得太疯了
They are peaking too early.
这不一定是好事
It might not be a good thing.
别被对方牵着走
Don't let them control the pace.
打出我们自己的节奏
Let's find our own.
争取拿回这局
Let's win the set!
一 二 加油
One, two, come on!
这一局对双方都非常关键 尤其是中国队
It's a crucial set for both teams, especially for China.
要转守为攻 郎平
Turn defense into attack, Ping!
问小袁数据有了吗
Ask Yuan for the stats.
郎导 巴西队现在12号进攻比较多
Coach, their No. 12 is leading the attack.
斜线的成功率比较高
Her diagonal stats are really good.
小丽
Yunli!
拦防重点人 抓她斜线
Track her, block her diagonals!
发六号位
Serve to Area 6.
郎平在向张常宁布置战术
Coach Lang gives tactics to Changning.
恐怕要发球找人
Maybe she's looking for weakness.
张常宁果然发给了六号位的娜塔莉姬
She's targeting Natalia at Area 6.
漂亮
Brilliant!
稳住
Don't rush.
巴西队失误了
Brazil makes a mistake.
张常宁继续发六号位
Changning serves to Area 6 again.
破坏巴西队一传
Brazil's first pass is disrupted.
中国队吊球得分
China wins another point with a tip.
郎导准确找到了对方的薄弱环节
Lang Ping has finally found the weakness of her opponent.
线路变一下
Change it up!
第二局中国队开局打得非常好
China opens the 2nd set with great game.
郎平及时调整战术
Coach Lang changes their tactics timely.
利用发球抑制住了巴西队的进攻
China's serves deter Brazil's attack.
中国队的表现和第一局比赛
Comparing with its performance in the previous set,
简直是判若两队
China looks like a different team now.
漂亮 朱婷高高跃起
Great one! Ting jumps high.
一记重扣得分
Her powerful spike wins China another point!
现在双方回到了同一起跑线
The two teams are at the same starting line again.
换魏秋月 颜妮 张常宁 首发
Have Qiuyue, Ni and Changning to start.
跳快了
Jumping too early!
魏秋 给快球
Qiuyue, try quick sets.
漂亮颜妮扣得非常果断
Good one! A decisive spike from Yan Ni.
吊球 多打吊球
Play more tips.
现在中国队完全打开了
China is playing without fear.
朱 好球
Ting, good one!
对
That's right.
第三轮 两点换三点
The 3rd rotation, 3 attacks from the front.
让晓彤热身
Tell Xiaotong to warm up.
她们主攻累了 就照这样进攻
Their hitter is tired, carry on like this.
惠若琪体力下降
Ruoqi is tired.
郎导请求换人
Coach Lang is making a substitution.
- 她是谁 - 但她换上来的居然是
- Who is this? - The player coming on is
之前没怎么上过场的刘晓彤
Xiaotong, who hasn't played much so far.
不清楚 没有她的大赛纪录
We don't have information about her.
魏秋 给速度
Qiuyue, faster.
刘晓彤扣球
Xiaotong spikes.
刘晓彤作为奇兵上场毫不手软
Xiaotong is a relentless surprise.
完全打破了巴西队的部署
She is destroying Brazil's approach.
郎平的用人太神了
Lang Ping works her magic again!
一个小时以前如果我告诉你
If I told you one hour ago
中国队现在是2比1 领先巴西队
that China would be leading 2:1 now
没有人会相信
no one would have believed me.
漂亮
Good one!
好
Good!
到了决胜局了
It's the last set.
她们是主场 压力更大
They are under great pressure on home turf.
我现在真想往你们血管里注进几公升水
I want to fill your blood with gallons of water.
我们要放下杂念
Let go of your other thoughts.
强攻要耐心
Be patient with attacks.
打不死上网要快
Block faster when they counter.
我们明明是实力更强的一方
We're obviously the stronger team.
你们要相信在白天消耗的神 在夜里会补给你们
The Gods will give back what you used in the day.
不要给她们任何机会
Don't leave them any chance.
打出气势
Give your all
不留遗憾
leave no regrets!
姑娘们去猛烈地击垮她们
Let's beat their ass!
好不好
Got it?
一 二 加油
One, two, fight!
观众朋友们现在是第五局
Dear audiences, the match has come to the 5th set.
比赛到了最白热化的阶段
The court is at a fever pitch.
现场的声浪都要把屋顶掀翻了
The crowd's roar is blowing the roof off.
我解说比赛从来没有这么紧张过
I've never been this nervous as a commentator.
决胜局比赛只有十五分
The final game is only 15 points
双方都有机会
so anyone can win this.
今天大家有什么就说什么
Everyone should come out with their thoughts.
不留遗憾
Leave no regrets
行吗
okay?
扣球 漂亮
Spike! Great one!
你们下次还有机会
You guys still have a chance
但我肯定是最后一届了
but this will be my last Olympics.
那我说吧
Let me start with myself.
小组赛我打得很差
I haven't been playing well.
明天让我首发其实我挺害怕的
I'm anxious about being a starter tomorrow.
但我不想给大家拖后腿
I don't want to let you down.
我会跟大家一起顶的
I promise to fight as hard as I can.
丁霞二次球 有了
Xia attacks from first pass, score!
我上步还是上得特别早
I've been jumping too early
也发不上力
and my spikes were weak.
巴西队大力扣球
Brazil attacks with a heavy spike.
这个球防起来了
It's saved.
但我明天一定会去改
Tomorrow I will avoid such mistakes.
只要你们敢给 我就敢扣
You set it, and I'll spike it.
张常宁果断下手 得分了
A decisive spike from Changning, score!
我觉得我这几场比赛
In previous matches
进攻节奏不好
my rhythm has been off.
然后拦网也老是乱扑
And my blocks are all over the place.
玥儿
Yue
情绪是你的优势
you are good with your emotions.
明天上场先喊起来
You should scream your head off.
魏秋月球传得很好
Great set from Qiuyue.
袁心玥扣球
Yue spikes!
朱婷再扣 中国队得分
Ting spikes again! China scores!
郎导最后一个选我进入奥运会名单的
I was the last name in the squad
可是我的比赛打得一点也不好
and I haven't been playing well.
来都来了 别想那么多
Don't overthink it since you're already here.
明天上场我给你兜着
Just go for it, I'll be behind you.
我做了两次心脏手术
I had 2 heart surgeries.
不知道能扛到什么时候
I don't know how my body will hold up.
双方你来我往
The ball is back-and-forth.
但只要我站在场上
But as long as I'm on court
我就豁出去了
I'll give it my all.
没关系 惠
Ruoqi, it's alright
我们四个主攻一起扛
we four outside hitters are in this together.
中国队多点进攻
China attacks from multiple positions.
在场上完全占据了优势
They are having full control on court.
对啊
Yes
大不了明天用脸去顶
I'll even head the ball.
林莉的防守非常顽强
Lin Li's defense is stout.
球垫起来了
She digs the ball!
中国队打出了开赛以来最好的状态
China is on top of their game now!
巴西队把球高高垫过网
Brazil tips the ball high over the net.
中国队组织进攻
China gathers for an attack.
朱婷四号位扣球
Ting spikes from Area 4.
球打中了
She hits it in!
但是裁判示意扣球出界
The referee rules the ball is out of bounds.
郎指导提出挑战
Coach Lang requests a challenge.
我们耐心等待一会
Let's wait for the result.
球扣在界内
In bounds.
中国队挑战成功
China's challenge is successful.
中国队2号换转到后排
Their No. 2 is in the back row.
她的一传是弱项 击溃她
Receive is her weakness, target her.
这几个球专门针对朱婷
They've been targeting Ting.
巴西队利用她一传不稳定 来破坏中国队节奏
And is using this to break China's rhythm.
朱婷
Ting
你是我见过最棒的球员
out of all the players I've trained
包括老外
you're the best.
我为你骄傲
I'm proud of you.
你不用成为我
You don't need to be me.
你只要成为你自己
You just have to be yourself.
巴西队发球
Brazil serves.
刘晓彤顶住了一传
Xiaotong manages to receive it.
朱婷打出了一记超手球
Ting spikes over a block!
势不可挡
She's unstoppable!
巴西一传垫飞了
Brazil's receive flies off
现在是反击的机会
a chance to counter.
朱婷扣球得分
Ting spikes a point!
郎导请求换人
Coach Lang is making a substitution.
她换上大赛经验丰富的惠若琪
Ruoqi, with the big games experience.
让朱婷下场休息
Allowing Ting to rest.
惠若琪球风稳健
Ruoqi helps stabilise the team.
巴西队还是紧紧咬住 12比13
Brazil keeps the game tight, 12:13.
下网
Serves into the net.
中国队获得赛点
Match point for China.
现在中国队即将淘汰世界第一的巴西队
China is on the verge of eliminating the world No. 1, Brazil.
巴西队员希望借助主场观众的吶喊声
The Brazil team hopes use their roaring crowd
在气势上压倒中国队
to overwhelm the China team.
三号位重扣
A heavy spike from Area 3.
巴西队扳回一分
Brazil gets a point.
14比13
14:13.
郎指导请求暂停
Coach Lang asks for a timeout.
这个球你准备怎么打
How are you going to play?
朱婷在后排 位置不好
Ting's in back row, it'd more demanding.
保险一点 我给徐云丽打
I'll set it for Yunli, to be safe.
大胆组织 关键时刻
Be bold. This is the moment.
别保守
Don't play it safe.
你做好准备
Get ready.
放开打
And show them what you've got!
电视机前的观众朋友们
Audiences in front of the TV
比赛来到了最关键的一球
this is the deciding point of the match.
徐云丽和魏秋月是老搭档
Yunli and Qiuyue are old teammates
应该很有默契
they should be a veteran duo.
朱婷虽然今天发挥很亮眼
Ting is exceptional today
但她现在在后排
but she's in the back row.
给她打这个球 实在是太冒险了
Passing the ball to her is risky.
现在巴西队发球
Brazil serves.
张常宁一传到位
Changning receives well.
徐云丽开始跑动
Yunli is off running.
魏秋月和徐云丽在关键时刻
Qiuyue and Yunli's back set attack
配合过多次背飞战术
has worked many times before.
但徐云丽要面对全世界最强的拦网
In front of Yunli is the best middle blocker.
魏秋月出乎意料地把球传到了三号位
To everyone's surprise, Qiuyue sets the ball to Area 3.
朱婷后攻
Back row attack from Ting.
喂
Hello?